<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>My bits</title>
    <link>http://lpantano.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://lpantano.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>My bits</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://lpantano.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>My bits</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women in Life Sciences: How do we Close the Gender Gap in Leadership?</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/biotalent2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/biotalent2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inside a Bioinformatics Startup – with NextRNA Therapeutics</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/nextflow2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/nextflow2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academia EOF &amp;&amp; cat &gt; eGenesis &lt;&lt;</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/2019/2019-10-03-move-to-egenesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2019 17:42:40 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/2019/2019-10-03-move-to-egenesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you came here it is because the twitter wasn’t enough for you and somehow you are curious about why I moved to industry after so many years in academia. Although I am sure this event has a p-value &amp;gt; 0.05 , then &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.americanscientist.org/article/the-statistical-crisis-in-science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;~is not significant.~ &lt;/a&gt;(wink wink)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you know me a little bit, you may be surprised about this change in my career. It was a difficult decision for me, indeed. Somehow, I see this as a no turning back point, maybe is not totally true.  I have advocated, so many times, that my reason to stay in academia is that there are more chances to help each other, to create open-source resources, to move forward together… that somehow, moving to industry is the opposite of all that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, academia couldn’t give me more, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel I was giving more. I decided a while ago to give up on a tenured career and dedicated many years to work inside a core facility at HSPH. I met awesome people, I learned from the best, I got to work with really amazing data…but there is a price for that. Being mainly an analyst made me see some parts that weren’t that nice. I realized many researchers will see you as a machine of producing data/figures/tables. They only care about that figure that will show the reviewer they were right. I saw how I couldn’t get into the project more than for a &amp;lsquo;quick&amp;rsquo; analysis of the data, without getting into the biology or the goal of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only that, but I realized I hadn’t a future, I would be stuck forever in that position, it was a senior position, but I really want to move forward and up. And after my second try at MIT, in another Bioinformatics core, I didn’t see that coming any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was time to think about why I am in the science business. Somehow, when I was young, I felt attracted to this world. I forgot about why, but what I liked was to work with people, together, to understand the molecular biology of a system. There was something else, it needed to be something that I believed in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is when &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.egenesisbio.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;eGenesis Bio - Engineering Life&lt;/a&gt; came into my sight. The vision is simple: stop people dying because of a lack of compatible organs. The solution is almost science fiction: genome editing on pigs to clone them and use those organs in humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to meet them, and I found a wonderful team and a challenging project. It was time to decide, and it was hard. Curiously, the main reasons that were stopping for saying yes, were mainly related to fear. A fear that the system put on me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to publish &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;, you need to be known on twitter, to be invited to conferences… otherwise, you won’t move forward in your career, you won’t have a good job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, I don’t have first-author papers in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;, I am not ~famous on twitter,~ I am not invited to conferences, and leaving academia means I will never be that, for sure. I felt like a failure. Because I didn’t get any of that, and I will never get it. And somehow, I ended up thinking that was the only way to measure success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily me, I read this book I had since months ago: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/dp/1524762334/ref=cm_sw_em_r_mt_dp_U_hlNLDb98S9NTP&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brave, Not Perfect: Reshma Saujani&lt;/a&gt;, and helped me to see that feeling, those thoughts, as something external and not something that was part of me. At this point, I really wanted to forget about all the pressure I had on my shoulders and do just my job, my job on something that I consider relevant, and with the people I want to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, of course, I decided to move on. If the only reason why you won’t make a change is because of fear to fail/change/future, then you should definitely do it. (&lt;em&gt;read the book, seriously&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, I got to meet myself again, after so many years doing what the system has told me to do to get a good job, and have a future. I remembered what is my passion, I remembered to believe in myself, and let life to reward my decisions differently (this I will know in a year or so).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other things I did meanwhile I was in this crisis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write my research, teaching and diversity statements and apply for Associate Professors to 5 different positions to 5 different universities. I didn’t pass any filter.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good mental exercise, yes, I know, 5 positions are nothing, you should apply to 30, or that was the main advice I got.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I explored to change totally my career, as a project manager or data scientist in a non-biomedical field.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took some courses, and I didn’t feel the click that I expect when you are in the right place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I felt miserable and with the lowest self-esteem in my life.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I started climbing indoors and working out with a personal trainer. All those negative feelings went away with time. Now I can do 2 pulls-up is a row for the first time in my life at the age of 37.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-cell cloning of human T-cell lines reveals clonal variation in cell death responses to chemotherapeutics.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/hanlon-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/hanlon-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to set up cellranger to make your hpc admin happy</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/2019/2019-07-12-cellranger-efficiency-in-hpc-copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/2019/2019-07-12-cellranger-efficiency-in-hpc-copy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I found myself to force to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.10xgenomics.com/single-cell-gene-expression/software/pipelines/latest/advanced/cluster-mode&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;cellranger&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile it helps a lot to
run from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.illumina.com/informatics/sequencing-data-analysis/sequence-file-formats.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bcl&lt;/a&gt; files to single cell counts matrixes, I discovered that is
quite difficult to control many options related to optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to run more than 200 samples in a short time of period. In my current
position at MIT, I joined the OpenMind cluster in the McGovern institute. I was
pleased to find a very flexible cluster, but as any other cluster you need to
respect other users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My samples are human samples, so I need a lot of memory so &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alexdobin/STAR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;STAR&lt;/a&gt; can run. The
command line is easy to set up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cellranger count --id=SAMPLE --transcriptome=GRCh38_pre_mRNA --fastqs=PATH2FASTQS --sample=SAMPLE&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, that is in local mode. If you want to set up a job to a cluster,
it would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash
#SBATCH -N 1
#SBATCH -c 6
#SBATCH --mem=12000
#SBATCH -t 0-48:00:00
#SBATCH -J cellr
#SBATCH -e job-counts.e
#SBATCH -o job-counts.o
## SBATCH --mail-type=END,FAIL # this line is commented
## SBATCH --mail-user=user@mit.edu  # this line is commented

cellranger count --id=SAMPLE --transcriptome=GRCh38_pre_mRNA \
          --fastqs=PATH2FASTQS --sample=SAMPLE \
          --localcores=6 --localmem=120

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem with that is you are using 120G during all the process that could
go to 1-2 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discovered that you can setup the &lt;code&gt; cluster&lt;/code&gt; mode to make &lt;code&gt;cellranger&lt;/code&gt; to send
jobs to the cluster. However, &lt;code&gt;slurm&lt;/code&gt; is not a option to the documentation, BUT
you can specify a template file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash
#SBATCH -J __MRO_JOB_NAME__
#SBATCH -N 1
#SBATCH -c __MRO_THREADS__
#SBATCH --mem=__MRO_MEM_GB__G
#SBATCH -o __MRO_STDOUT__
#SBATCH -e __MRO_STDERR__
#SBATCH -t 0-48:00:00
#SBATCH --qos=&amp;quot;normal&amp;quot;

 __MRO_CMD__
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cellranger count --id=SAMPLE --transcriptome=GRCh38_pre_mRNA \
          --fastqs=PATH2FASTQS --sample=SAMPLE \
          --jobmode=slurm.template \
          --maxjobs=3 --jobinterval=1000

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was feeling victory, ha ha ha, BUT I saw that the &lt;code&gt;ALIGN&lt;/code&gt; step was requesting
220G of memory&amp;hellip;. WHAT!!!!!????? or better &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WATTT????!!!!!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;note&lt;/strong&gt;: this is set up during genome generation with the parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
    --memgb=&amp;lt;num&amp;gt;       Maximum memory (GB) used when aligning reads with STAR.
                          Defaults to 16.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;note&lt;/strong&gt;: default is 16G but if I use that then my jobs are cancelled because using more memory than requested, as I expected considering STAR needs more than that for human genome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I didn&amp;rsquo;t look at the first place I should have looked, but it took me
some time to discovered that the memory is coming from a file in the reference
genome folder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cat GRCh38_pre_mRNA/reference.json
{
    &amp;quot;fasta_hash&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;954a9c3916ef1544c9358445440b9683fc061c71&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;genomes&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;GRCh38_pre_mRNA&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;gtf_hash&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;12aae438159b35282adaf643cca4dc5887b0448a&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;input_fasta_files&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;Homo_sapiens.GRCh38.dna.toplevel.fa&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;input_gtf_files&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;GRC38_preRNA.gtf&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;mem_gb&amp;quot;: 220,
    &amp;quot;mkref_version&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;3.0.2&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;threads&amp;quot;: 24,
    &amp;quot;version&amp;quot;: null
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that when I found, after 100 &lt;code&gt;ls/cat/less/grep&lt;/code&gt;, this file with these
lines of code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cellranger-3.0.2/cellranger-cs/3.0.2/lib/python/cellranger/utils.py
def _load_reference_metadata_file(reference_path):
    reference_metadata_file = os.path.join(reference_path, cr_constants.REFERENCE_METADATA_FILE)
    with open(reference_metadata_file, &#39;r&#39;) as f:
        return json.load(f)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, easy peasy, I changed that to 110. I relaunched the job I was using to test,
and found that it was still setting up 220G&amp;hellip;WHY!?!!? well, it seems if you relaunch
in a step where the alignment has already begun, there is a cache for the resources.
So after more time trying to figure out this and asking myself, why I decided my
career path to be bioinformatics, I tried a fresh start and&amp;hellip;IT WORKED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How happy one can be to see a job requesting the expected resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incredible happy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went a step further, and looked how much memory actually it was using during the
alignment step, and I saw that actually only needs 64G, so I updated to 72G, to
gain more karma from the HPC world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one more thing, that will set jobs of 72G and 4 cores, if you want to
increase the number of cores, then use this option &lt;code&gt;--mempercore 6&lt;/code&gt; or whatever number
that you want: &lt;code&gt;mempercore = 72G/final_cores&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;workflow&#34;&gt;Workflow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I felt that I was doing my best to behave and avoid making angry other
people using the hpc. The final setup looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;meta-script to send all the samples to a master job: &lt;code&gt;runner.sh&lt;/code&gt;. It accepts
a file where first column is &lt;code&gt;sample name&lt;/code&gt; and second column is &lt;code&gt;fastq_path&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;set -o pipefail  # trace ERR through pipes
set -o errtrace  # trace ERR through &#39;time command&#39; and other functions
set -o nounset   ## set -u : exit the script if you try to use an uninitialised variable
set -o errexit   ## set -e : exit the script if any statement returns a non-true return value
# set -v # you can uncomment all these lines to have a better debugging
# set -x
# export PS4=&#39;+(${BASH_SOURCE}:${LINENO}): ${FUNCNAME[0]:+${FUNCNAME[0]}(): }&#39;

while IFS=&amp;quot; &amp;quot; read -r sample paths

do

RUN=0
if [[ ! -e $sample/filtered_feature_bc_matrix.h5 ]]; then
    RUN=1 # run if the final output is not there yet
fi

if [[  -e  $sample/_lock ]]; then
    echo $sample is locked, please:
    echo rm $sample/_lock
    RUN=0 # but don&#39;t do anything if is locked
fi

if [[ $RUN == 1 ]]; then
    echo sbatch -J $sample -o logs/$sample.o -e logs/$sample.e scripts/om-counts-cluster.slurm $sample $paths
    sbatch -J $sample -o logs/$sample.o -e logs/$sample.e scripts/om-counts-cluster.slurm $sample $paths
fi

done &amp;lt; $1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SBATCH script with cellranger command: &lt;code&gt;counter.slurm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash
#SBATCH -N 1
#SBATCH -c 1
#SBATCH --mem=6000
#SBATCH -t 0-48:00:00
# SBATCH -J &amp;quot;cellr-$1&amp;quot;
# SBATCH -e job-counts-$1.e
# SBATCH -o job-counts-$1.o
## SBATCH --mail-type=END,FAIL # this line is commented
## SBATCH --mail-user=user@mit.edu  # this line is commented

SCRIPTPATH=&amp;quot;PATHTOSCRIPTS&amp;quot;
cellranger count --id=$1 --transcriptome=GRCh38_pre_mRNA --fastqs=$2 --sample=$1 --jobmode=$SCRIPTPATH/slurm.template --maxjobs=3 --jobinterval=1000

if [ $? -eq 0 ]; then
    echo OK
    mv $1 results/.
else
    echo $1 FAIL
fi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;template script for &lt;code&gt;cellranger&lt;/code&gt; as shown above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-tips&#34;&gt;Other tips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;mxjobs=3&lt;/code&gt; to avoid a lot of jobs. I am testing how things go, this could be spanned to bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;jobinterval=1000&lt;/code&gt; to avoid sending jobs at the same time, just in case, but I don&amp;rsquo;t have any proof to support this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;happiness in bioinformatics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sex Differences in Adrenal Bmal1 Deletion-Induced Augmentation of Glucocorticoid Responses to Stress and ACTH in Mice.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/engeland-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/engeland-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A High-Throughput Screening Identifies MicroRNA Inhibitors That Influence Neuronal Maintenance and/or Response to Oxidative Stress.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pallarsalbanell-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pallarsalbanell-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi omics analysis of fibrotic kidneys in two mouse models.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pavkovic-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pavkovic-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to set up public dataset analysis with bcbio-nextgen</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/2019/2019-04-05-how-to-setup-remote-samples-with-bcbio/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2019 10:13:02 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/2019/2019-04-05-how-to-setup-remote-samples-with-bcbio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bcbio/bcbio-nextgen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bcbio-nextgen&lt;/a&gt; for the analysis of sequencing data, mainly, (sc)RNAseq,
smallRNAseq, DNASeq and ChIPSeq. It is not rare that we get collaborators who
wants to re-analyze public data-set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside &lt;code&gt;bcbio&lt;/code&gt;, we have &lt;a href=&#34;https://bcbio-nextgen.readthedocs.io/en/latest/contents/configuration.html#multiple-files-per-sample&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bcbio_prepare_samples.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
to help to merge multiple
files that belong to the same sample into one file to make easier the configuration
of &lt;strong&gt;bcbio&lt;/strong&gt;. We extended this script to pull down data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GEO&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SRA&lt;/a&gt; repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have &lt;strong&gt;bcbio&lt;/strong&gt;. installed, you can create a &lt;code&gt;example.csv&lt;/code&gt; file like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;samplenames,description
GSM3508215,HEK293T
SRR8311268,Hela
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bcbio_prepare_samples.py --csv example.csv --out fastq
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will download and create all the files inside &lt;code&gt;fastq&lt;/code&gt; folder. If the samples
is paired-end, it will generated the two associated files: R1 and R2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool options to use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;--remove-source&lt;/code&gt;: if you want to keep only final files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can use full FTP addresses as well under &lt;code&gt;samplenames&lt;/code&gt; column&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nextflow.io/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NextFlow&lt;/a&gt; accepts these SRA ids as well, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nextflow.io/blog/2019/release-19.03.0-edge.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;take a look&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&#34;https://ewels.github.io/sra-explorer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sra-explorer&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ewels&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Phil Ewels&lt;/a&gt;
will create a bash script to download the FASTQ files and It has a great search engine where
you can use any of these terms to find your public data:
&lt;code&gt;GSE30567, SRP043510, PRJEB8073, ERP009109 or human liver miRNA.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only advantage of &lt;strong&gt;bcbio&lt;/strong&gt; is that in the case of multiple files associated to the same
sample, it will merge the files together. For instance, if you search in &lt;strong&gt;sra-explorer&lt;/strong&gt; for this&lt;br&gt;
term: &lt;code&gt;GSM2598386&lt;/code&gt;, you see that multiple files. &lt;strong&gt;bcbio&lt;/strong&gt;. will merge all  of them into one and
you can run your pipeline directly afterwards. And pretty convenient if you
use any of the &lt;strong&gt;bcbio&lt;/strong&gt; pipelines :).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;happiness in bioinformatics: when your collaborators give you  a CSV file
with all the metadata for your raw data and they match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>miRNA variants (isomiRs): real molecules or sequencing artifacts?</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/bioclub2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/bioclub2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary and functional impact of common polymorphic inversions in the human genome</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/giner-2019-evolutionary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/giner-2019-evolutionary/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sex-dependent changes in miRNA expression in the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis following stress</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/mavrikaki-2019-sex/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/mavrikaki-2019-sex/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MiRNA Wars: The isomiRs menance</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/big2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 15:06:12 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/big2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unification of miRNA and isomiR research: the mirGFF3 format and the mirtop API</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/desvignes-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/desvignes-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get colors for your heatmap annotation</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2018-09-21-colors-for-annotations-for-heatmaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 10:13:02 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2018-09-21-colors-for-annotations-for-heatmaps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post will show how to configure quickly the colors for the annotation of rows/columns that go on top or on the side of a heatmap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I normally use &lt;code&gt;pheatmap&lt;/code&gt; a lot. Recently I discovered &lt;code&gt;ComplexHeatmap&lt;/code&gt;. In both cases I spend always sometime changing the colors of the annotations. I ended up coding a function inside my package &lt;code&gt;DEGreport&lt;/code&gt; to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a data.frame with metadata data information will do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;white-black scale for numerical variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blue-orange for categorical values with only two categories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Set2&lt;/code&gt; palette for categorical values with more than two categories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three color sets can be changed using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/DEGreport/reference/degColors.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;parameters function&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(DEGreport)
library(stemHypoxia)
data(stemHypoxia)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to use this &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/data/experiment/html/stemHypoxia.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;stemcell experiment dataset&lt;/a&gt; I found randomly in Bioconductor page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;exp = as.matrix(M[,3:30])
rownames(exp) = M[,2]
rownames(design) = colnames(exp)
design = design[,c(1:2)]
design$time = as.factor(design$time)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll find the most variable genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;most_variable = names(tail(sort(apply(exp, 1, sd)), 1000))
design$mean_gene = colMeans(exp[most_variable,])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we can plot the heatmap with new colors with need to specify each variable at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(pheatmap)
pheatmap(exp[most_variable,], scale = &amp;quot;row&amp;quot;, show_rownames = FALSE,
         annotation_col = design,
         annotation_colors = degColors(design))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/raw/master/code-blog/degcolor/degcolors_files/figure-markdown_github/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use &lt;code&gt;ComplexHeatmap&lt;/code&gt; you can activate &lt;code&gt;col_fun = TRUE&lt;/code&gt; to get it working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R Session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;devtools::session_info()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: &#39;DESCRIPTION&#39; file has an &#39;Encoding&#39; field and re-encoding is not
## possible

## Session info -------------------------------------------------------------

##  setting  value
##  version  R version 3.5.1 (2018-07-02)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0
##  ui       X11
##  language (EN)
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8
##  tz       America/New_York
##  date     2018-09-21

## Packages -----------------------------------------------------------------

##  package              * version   date       source
##  acepack                1.4.1     2016-10-29 cran (@1.4.1)
##  annotate               1.58.0    2018-05-01 cran (@1.58.0)
##  AnnotationDbi          1.42.1    2018-05-08 Bioconductor
##  assertthat             0.2.0     2017-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  backports              1.1.2     2017-12-13 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  base                 * 3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  base64enc              0.1-3     2015-07-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  bindr                  0.1.1     2018-03-13 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  bindrcpp               0.2.2     2018-03-29 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  Biobase                2.40.0    2018-05-01 Bioconductor
##  BiocGenerics           0.26.0    2018-05-01 Bioconductor
##  BiocParallel           1.14.2    2018-07-08 cran (@1.14.2)
##  bit                    1.1-14    2018-05-29 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  bit64                  0.9-7     2017-05-08 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  bitops                 1.0-6     2013-08-17 cran (@1.0-6)
##  blob                   1.1.1     2018-03-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  broom                  0.5.0     2018-07-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  checkmate              1.8.5     2017-10-24 cran (@1.8.5)
##  circlize               0.4.4     2018-06-10 cran (@0.4.4)
##  cluster                2.0.7-1   2018-04-13 CRAN (R 3.5.1)
##  colorspace             1.3-2     2016-12-14 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  compiler               3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  ComplexHeatmap         1.18.1    2018-06-19 cran (@1.18.1)
##  ConsensusClusterPlus   1.44.0    2018-05-01 cran (@1.44.0)
##  cowplot                0.9.3     2018-07-15 cran (@0.9.3)
##  crayon                 1.3.4     2017-09-16 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  data.table             1.11.4    2018-05-27 cran (@1.11.4)
##  datasets             * 3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  DBI                    1.0.0     2018-05-02 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  DEGreport            * 1.17.5    2018-09-04 local (lpantano/DEGreport@NA)
##  DelayedArray           0.6.5     2018-08-15 cran (@0.6.5)
##  DESeq2                 1.20.0    2018-05-01 Bioconductor
##  devtools               1.13.6    2018-06-27 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  digest                 0.6.16    2018-08-22 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  dplyr                  0.7.6     2018-06-29 CRAN (R 3.5.1)
##  edgeR                  3.22.3    2018-06-21 cran (@3.22.3)
##  evaluate               0.11      2018-07-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  foreign                0.8-71    2018-07-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  Formula                1.2-3     2018-05-03 cran (@1.2-3)
##  genefilter             1.62.0    2018-05-01 cran (@1.62.0)
##  geneplotter            1.58.0    2018-05-01 cran (@1.58.0)
##  GenomeInfoDb           1.16.0    2018-05-01 cran (@1.16.0)
##  GenomeInfoDbData       1.1.0     2018-08-31 Bioconductor
##  GenomicRanges          1.32.6    2018-07-20 cran (@1.32.6)
##  GetoptLong             0.1.7     2018-06-10 cran (@0.1.7)
##  ggdendro               0.1-20    2016-04-27 cran (@0.1-20)
##  ggplot2                3.0.0     2018-07-03 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  ggrepel                0.8.0     2018-05-09 cran (@0.8.0)
##  GlobalOptions          0.1.0     2018-06-09 cran (@0.1.0)
##  glue                   1.3.0     2018-07-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  graphics             * 3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  grDevices            * 3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  grid                   3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  gridExtra              2.3       2017-09-09 cran (@2.3)
##  gtable                 0.2.0     2016-02-26 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  Hmisc                  4.1-1     2018-01-03 cran (@4.1-1)
##  htmlTable              1.12      2018-05-26 cran (@1.12)
##  htmltools              0.3.6     2017-04-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  htmlwidgets            1.2       2018-04-19 cran (@1.2)
##  IRanges                2.14.11   2018-08-24 Bioconductor
##  knitr                  1.20      2018-02-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  lasso2                 1.2-19    2014-05-31 cran (@1.2-19)
##  lattice                0.20-35   2017-03-25 CRAN (R 3.5.1)
##  latticeExtra           0.6-28    2016-02-09 cran (@0.6-28)
##  lazyeval               0.2.1     2017-10-29 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  limma                  3.36.3    2018-08-25 cran (@3.36.3)
##  locfit                 1.5-9.1   2013-04-20 cran (@1.5-9.1)
##  logging                0.7-103   2013-04-12 cran (@0.7-103)
##  magrittr               1.5       2014-11-22 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  MASS                   7.3-50    2018-04-30 CRAN (R 3.5.1)
##  Matrix                 1.2-14    2018-04-13 CRAN (R 3.5.1)
##  matrixStats            0.54.0    2018-07-23 cran (@0.54.0)
##  memoise                1.1.0     2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  methods              * 3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  mnormt                 1.5-5     2016-10-15 cran (@1.5-5)
##  munsell                0.5.0     2018-06-12 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  nlme                   3.1-137   2018-04-07 CRAN (R 3.5.1)
##  nnet                   7.3-12    2016-02-02 CRAN (R 3.5.1)
##  Nozzle.R1              1.1-1     2013-05-15 cran (@1.1-1)
##  parallel               3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  pheatmap             * 1.0.10    2018-05-19 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  pillar                 1.3.0     2018-07-14 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  pkgconfig              2.0.2     2018-08-16 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  plyr                   1.8.4     2016-06-08 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  psych                  1.8.4     2018-05-06 cran (@1.8.4)
##  purrr                  0.2.5     2018-05-29 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  R6                     2.2.2     2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  RColorBrewer           1.1-2     2014-12-07 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  Rcpp                   0.12.18   2018-07-23 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  RCurl                  1.95-4.11 2018-07-15 cran (@1.95-4.)
##  reshape                0.8.7     2017-08-06 cran (@0.8.7)
##  rjson                  0.2.20    2018-06-08 cran (@0.2.20)
##  rlang                  0.2.2     2018-08-16 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  rmarkdown              1.10      2018-06-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  rpart                  4.1-13    2018-02-23 CRAN (R 3.5.1)
##  rprojroot              1.3-2     2018-01-03 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  RSQLite                2.1.1     2018-05-06 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  rstudioapi             0.7       2017-09-07 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  S4Vectors              0.18.3    2018-06-08 Bioconductor
##  scales                 1.0.0     2018-08-09 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  shape                  1.4.4     2018-02-07 cran (@1.4.4)
##  splines                3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  stats                * 3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  stats4                 3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  stemHypoxia          * 1.16.0    2018-09-21 Bioconductor
##  stringi                1.2.4     2018-07-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  stringr                1.3.1     2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  SummarizedExperiment   1.10.1    2018-05-11 Bioconductor
##  survival               2.42-6    2018-07-13 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  tibble                 1.4.2     2018-01-22 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  tidyr                  0.8.1     2018-05-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  tidyselect             0.2.4     2018-02-26 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  tools                  3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  utils                * 3.5.1     2018-07-05 local
##  withr                  2.1.2     2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  XML                    3.98-1.16 2018-08-19 cran (@3.98-1.)
##  xtable                 1.8-3     2018-08-29 cran (@1.8-3)
##  XVector                0.20.0    2018-05-01 cran (@0.20.0)
##  yaml                   2.2.0     2018-07-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)
##  zlibbioc               1.26.0    2018-05-01 cran (@1.26.0)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to plot miRNA, gene expression and functional analysis together</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2018-08-13-omic-figure-for-mirna-gene-functional-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2018-08-13-omic-figure-for-mirna-gene-functional-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post should show you an easy way to get the following data type
integrated into a figure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;functional enrichment analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gene expression data from any technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;miRNA expression data from any technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using the function &lt;code&gt;isoNetwork&lt;/code&gt; from the package &lt;code&gt;isomiRs&lt;/code&gt;, that of
course is developed by me :) My ego is not that big, it is just I wanted
a figure showing that information, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find any at a time,
but if you know any, tweet me about it to @lopantano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This function needs some pre-computed information, like the normalized
expression and the targeted genes by miRNAs. Normally, the significant
genes and miRNAs from a differentially expression analysis would do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first requirement is two have these two datasets into a
SummarizedExperiment object As an example, I am using the published data
from Folic Acid Mouse model (GSE65267) that has been analyzed with
bcbio-nextgen pipeline and bcbioRNASeq package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saved these analysis into an R object that contains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fa_mrna: gene expression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fa_mirna: miRNA expression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fa_cold: metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that, I ran DESeq2 to get the significant genes and miRNAs from the
comparison day14 vs day0 (normal).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&amp;gt; load(&amp;quot;fa_isonetwork.rda&amp;quot;)
R&amp;gt; library(isomiRs)
R&amp;gt; library(DESeq2)
R&amp;gt; library(SummarizedExperiment)
R&amp;gt;
R&amp;gt; mi_cold = fa_cold[colnames(fa_mirna), , drop = F]
R&amp;gt; mi_dse = DESeqDataSetFromMatrix(round(2^fa_mirna), mi_cold, design = ~day)
R&amp;gt; mi_dse = DESeq(mi_dse)
R&amp;gt; mi_res = results(mi_dse, name = &amp;quot;day_day14_vs_normal&amp;quot;)
R&amp;gt; mi_res = mi_res[!is.na(mi_res$padj), ]
R&amp;gt; mi_top = row.names(mi_res[mi_res$padj &amp;lt; 0.05, ])
R&amp;gt; mi_rse = SummarizedExperiment(assays = SimpleList(norm = fa_mirna), colData = mi_cold,
+     metadata = list(sign = mi_top))
R&amp;gt;
R&amp;gt; m_cold = fa_cold[colnames(fa_mrna), , drop = F]
R&amp;gt; m_dse = DESeqDataSetFromMatrix(round(2^fa_mrna), m_cold, design = ~day)
R&amp;gt; m_dse = DESeq(m_dse)
R&amp;gt; m_res = results(m_dse, name = &amp;quot;day_day14_vs_normal&amp;quot;)
R&amp;gt; m_res = m_res[!is.na(m_res$padj), ]
R&amp;gt; m_top = row.names(m_res[m_res$padj &amp;lt; 0.05, ])
R&amp;gt; m_rse = SummarizedExperiment(assays = SimpleList(norm = fa_mrna), colData = m_cold,
+     metadata = list(sign = m_top))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I ran the functional analysis with &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/clusterProfiler.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;clusterProfiler&lt;/code&gt; Bioc
package&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&amp;gt; library(org.Mm.eg.db)
R&amp;gt; library(clusterProfiler)
R&amp;gt;
R&amp;gt;
R&amp;gt; ego &amp;lt;- enrichGO(m_top, org.Mm.eg.db, &amp;quot;ENSEMBL&amp;quot;, ont = &amp;quot;MF&amp;quot;, universe = rownames(m_res))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, it could be anything as far as the table have the same naming
that the one coming from this package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last step before the real integration analysis, is to get the predicted
targets of the miRNA. This can be done with any package as far as you
get a table with two columns: gene and mirna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used two options, one using the already implemented code in the
package (that uses targetscan database):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&amp;gt; library(targetscan.Mm.eg.db)
R&amp;gt; m2t = mirna2targetscan(mi_top, species = &amp;quot;mmu&amp;quot;, org = org.Mm.eg.db, keytype = &amp;quot;ENSEMBL&amp;quot;)
R&amp;gt;
R&amp;gt; mirna_targets = findTargets(mi_rse, m_rse, m2t[, c(&amp;quot;ENSEMBL&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;mir&amp;quot;)], summarize = &amp;quot;day&amp;quot;,
+     min_cor = -0.7)

## Dimmension of cor matrix: 49 5233
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or using the function &lt;code&gt;get_multimir&lt;/code&gt; implemented on &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/multiMir.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;multiMiR&lt;/code&gt; Bioc
package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&amp;gt; library(multiMiR)
R&amp;gt; multimir_results &amp;lt;- get_multimir(org = &amp;quot;mmu&amp;quot;, mirna = mi_top, table = &amp;quot;validated&amp;quot;,
+     summary = TRUE)
R&amp;gt;
R&amp;gt; library(magrittr)
R&amp;gt; m2t_multimir = slot(multimir_results, &amp;quot;data&amp;quot;)[, c(&amp;quot;target_ensembl&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;mature_mirna_id&amp;quot;)] %&amp;gt;%
+     dplyr::filter(target_ensembl != &amp;quot;&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% dplyr::distinct()
R&amp;gt;
R&amp;gt; mirna_targets = findTargets(mi_rse, m_rse, m2t_multimir, summarize = &amp;quot;day&amp;quot;,
+     min_cor = -0.7)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, I ran &lt;code&gt;findTargets&lt;/code&gt; to use the expression data to make
sure the correlation between the miRNA and predicted gene is negative
since is the known biological function of miRNAs, being negative
modulators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we use &lt;code&gt;isoNetwork&lt;/code&gt; to put all the data together, and
&lt;code&gt;isoPlotNet&lt;/code&gt; to create the final figure with all information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&amp;gt; data &amp;lt;- isoNetwork(mi_rse, m_rse, min_fc = 0.1, summarize = &amp;quot;day&amp;quot;, target = mirna_targets,
+     enrich = ego)

## Dimmension of cor matrix: 49 305

R&amp;gt; isoPlotNet(data, minGenes = 1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/raw/master/code-blog/isonetwork/post_files/figure-markdown_strict/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an easy way to spot what pathways contain genes that are targeted
by miRNAs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this function won&amp;rsquo;t indicate if a pathway is enriched on miRNA
targets. It shows how these three different data set can be put together
to explore the relationship among them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;self-control in bioinformatics: be nice to your collaborator when
they can not open a TSV file with excel.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The circulating metabolome of human starvation</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/steinhauser-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/steinhauser-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>miRTOP: An open source community project for the development of a unified format file for miRNA data</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/bosc2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 13:13:02 -0900</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/bosc2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Circulating miRNAs, isomiRs and small RNA clusters in human plasma and breast milk</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/rubio-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/rubio-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>bcbioRNASeq: R package for bcbio RNA-seq analysis</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/steinbaugh-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/steinbaugh-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Subset of object creates bigger RDA file size than original object</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2017-08-24-subset-object-creates-bigger-file/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 17:50:01 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2017-08-24-subset-object-creates-bigger-file/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a funny story, and I will try to tell you how I realized I don&amp;rsquo;t know anything about R in 400 words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I work at the Bioinformatic Core at Harvard TH School. People who know us, or collaborate with us, knows that we mainly use
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chapmanb/bcbio-nextgen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bcbio&lt;/a&gt; to analyze sequencing data (check it out, super cool tool).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that we are working on is to load the data after &lt;code&gt;bcbio&lt;/code&gt; finishes into R to ease the downstream analysis.
For instance, for RNA-seq we have &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hbc/bcbioRnaSeq&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bcbioRnaSeq&lt;/a&gt; and for small RNA-seq we have &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/bcbioSmallRna&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bcbioSmallRna&lt;/a&gt;. In short,
these R packages make easy the task to load all the data generated by &lt;code&gt;bcbio&lt;/code&gt; and wrap many methods and functions to generate the most used figures/analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is not the story. The story is that the &lt;code&gt;bcbioRNADataSet&lt;/code&gt; object in those packages contains all the data in order to make easy the use of different counts matrix,
or subset to a smaller samples/genes. For instance, the object contains the DDS object (&lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/devel/bioc/html/DESeq2.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DESeq2&lt;/a&gt; &lt;code&gt;DESeqDataSet&lt;/code&gt;),
so we can use methods for this class or re-normalize at any point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, when we implemented the &lt;code&gt;[&lt;/code&gt; method (this allows to subset the object), we discovered that the
object coming from that method was twice as big when saving into an RDA file. For instance, if you have an object with 34K genes,
100 samples that would be 900Mb when saving, then you subset to 1000 genes and 8 samples, you would end up with a file being 1.6G.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is not nice, so I decided to play around. I don&amp;rsquo;t want you to read our code, because contains a lot of information, but feel free: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hbc/bcbioRnaseq/blob/master/R/methods-subset.R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;subset&lt;/a&gt;. I value your time, so this is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/blob/master/examples/subsetObject/subset.R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;dummy example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examples mainly creates different objects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dummyBig: 10K genes, 100 samples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dummySmall: 500 genes, 5 samples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dummySilly: subset of dummyBig using a silly function to subset, same size than dummySmall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dummySmart: subset of dummyBig using a smart function to subset, same size than dummySmall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should expect that &lt;code&gt;dummySilly&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dummySmart&lt;/code&gt; have a similar size than &lt;code&gt;dummySmall&lt;/code&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the size of RDA files for each of them (size in Kb):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;object&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;file&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;rdaSize&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;objSize&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;dummyBig&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;big.rda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2828.49 Kb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;1588 Kb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;dummySmall&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;micro.rda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;24.19 Kb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;42.6 Kb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;dummySilly&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;microSilly.rda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;4397.49 Kb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;43.2 Kb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;dummySmart&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;microSmart.rda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;22.38 Kb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;43.2 Kb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;rdaSize is the size of the file using &lt;code&gt;save(obj, file = fileName.rda&lt;/code&gt; function. objSize is the size in memory in R using the function &lt;code&gt;format(object.size(obj))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, &lt;code&gt;microSilly&lt;/code&gt; is almost twice the original data, but &lt;code&gt;microSmart&lt;/code&gt; is the expected size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know the exact reason, but the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/blob/master/examples/subsetObject/subset.R#L52&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;chunk of code&lt;/a&gt; that made the trick was to create an internal function to be called inside the method to re-generate the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/devel/bioc/html/DESeq2.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DESeq2&lt;/a&gt; object with the smaller size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know there should be a better way to avoid this, but this worked. If you have any comment/advice post it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/issues&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. My R session is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;honesty in bioinformatics: accept you develop without being an expert and that creates chaos.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;R version 3.4.1 (2017-06-30)
Platform: x86_64-apple-darwin15.6.0 (64-bit)
Running under: macOS Sierra 10.12.6

Matrix products: default
BLAS: /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/3.4/Resources/lib/libRblas.0.dylib
LAPACK: /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/3.4/Resources/lib/libRlapack.dylib

locale:
[1] en_US.UTF-8/en_US.UTF-8/en_US.UTF-8/C/en_US.UTF-8/en_US.UTF-8

attached base packages:
[1] parallel  stats4    methods   stats     graphics  grDevices utils
[8] datasets  base

other attached packages:
 [1] dplyr_0.7.2.9000           DESeq2_1.16.1
 [3] SummarizedExperiment_1.6.3 DelayedArray_0.2.7
 [5] matrixStats_0.52.2         Biobase_2.36.2
 [7] GenomicRanges_1.28.4       GenomeInfoDb_1.12.2
 [9] IRanges_2.10.2             S4Vectors_0.14.3
[11] BiocGenerics_0.22.0

loaded via a namespace (and not attached):
 [1] Rcpp_0.12.12            locfit_1.5-9.1          lattice_0.20-35
 [4] assertthat_0.2.0        digest_0.6.12           R6_2.2.2
 [7] plyr_1.8.4              backports_1.1.0         acepack_1.4.1
[10] RSQLite_2.0             highr_0.6               ggplot2_2.2.1
[13] zlibbioc_1.22.0         rlang_0.1.2.9000        lazyeval_0.2.0
[16] data.table_1.10.4       annotate_1.54.0         blob_1.1.0
[19] rpart_4.1-11            Matrix_1.2-10           checkmate_1.8.2
[22] splines_3.4.1           BiocParallel_1.10.1     geneplotter_1.54.0
[25] stringr_1.2.0           foreign_0.8-69          htmlwidgets_0.8
[28] RCurl_1.95-4.8          bit_1.1-12              munsell_0.4.3
[31] compiler_3.4.1          pkgconfig_2.0.1         base64enc_0.1-3
[34] htmltools_0.3.6         nnet_7.3-12             tibble_1.3.3.9001
[37] gridExtra_2.2.1         htmlTable_1.9           GenomeInfoDbData_0.99.0
[40] Hmisc_4.0-3             XML_3.98-1.9            bitops_1.0-6
[43] grid_3.4.1              xtable_1.8-2            gtable_0.2.0
[46] DBI_0.7                 magrittr_1.5            scales_0.4.1
[49] stringi_1.1.5           XVector_0.16.0          genefilter_1.58.1
[52] bindrcpp_0.2            latticeExtra_0.6-28     Formula_1.2-1
[55] RColorBrewer_1.1-2      tools_3.4.1             bit64_0.9-7
[58] glue_1.1.1.9000         survival_2.41-3         AnnotationDbi_1.38.2
[61] colorspace_1.3-2        cluster_2.0.6           memoise_1.1.0
[64] bindr_0.1               knitr_1.17

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DEGreport to plot nice RNA-seq figures</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2017-03-20-degreport-rnaseq-figures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 17:50:01 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2017-03-20-degreport-rnaseq-figures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Differentially gene expression analysis with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RNA-Seq&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RNA-seq&lt;/a&gt; data is quite common nowadays, and there are pretty good &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; packages for that: &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/limma.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;limma::voom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/DESeq2.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DESeq2&lt;/a&gt; &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code for that part is quite simple, being super quick to get a list of de-regulated genes. However, downstream analyses vary a lot depending on the project itself. But I found myself doing the same plots and analyses many times for different project, so I put together a bunch of plots and analyses using code from my colleagues at work (&lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.sph.harvard.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@HSPH bioinformatics core&lt;/a&gt;) and myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many possibilities, including QC figures, but the features that seem more interesting are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;plot of individual genes using multiple variables from the metadata. This would be an evolution of plotCounts function from DESeq2. Fig1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;plot volcano plots labeling some genes. Fig2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;clustering set of genes to find common patterns expression. Most useful for time seria data. You get as well the list of genes that follows that pattern, so you can use it for functional analysis, for instance. Fig3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;note: maybe some features only available with development version&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/raw/master/DEG_viz/figure/plots-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;fig1&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/raw/master/DEG_viz/figure/plots-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;fig2&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/raw/master/DEG_viz/figure/plots-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;fig3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Package available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/devel/bioc/html/DEGreport.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BioC page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/blob/master/DEG_viz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope you enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any suggestion and/or issue is welcome &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.bioconductor.org/p/new/post/?tag_val=DEGreport&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;sincerity in bioinformatics: try hard to explain the limitation of your analysis to non-computational researchers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maintenance of macrophage transcriptional programs and intestinal homeostasis by epigenetic reader SP140</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/mehta-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/mehta-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular, phenotypic, and sample-associated data to describe pluripotent stem cell lines and derivatives</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/daily-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/daily-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative analysis of LIN28-RNA binding sites identified at single nucleotide resolution</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/ransey-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/ransey-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empirical comparison of reduced representation bisulfite sequencing and Infinium BeadChip reproducibility and coverage of DNA methylation in humans</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/carmona-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/carmona-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Viewing RNA-seq data on the entire human genome</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/busby-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/busby-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of the small RNA transcriptome using the bcbio-nextgen python framework</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/bosc2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2016 14:54:17 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/talk/bosc2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>miRNA Annotation Tools Comparison</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2016-03-24-mirna-annotation-tools-comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 19:49:01 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2016-03-24-mirna-annotation-tools-comparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In summary: I will show which is the best miRNA mapping tool. I used several options for this benchmarking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;miraligner from &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/lpantano/seqbuster&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SeqBuster&lt;/a&gt; suit (I am one of the authors)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/bowtie2/index.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bowtie2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/index.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bowtie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.novocraft.com/main/index.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;novoalign&lt;/a&gt; from novocraft suit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://algorithms.cnag.cat/wiki/The_GEM_library&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GEM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://arn.ugr.es/srnabench/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;srnabench&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.seqan.de/projects/MicroRazerS.html.&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;microrazer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alexdobin/STAR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;STAR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mirexpress.mbc.nctu.edu.tw/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;miRExpress&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that these are the most used, and other not used but good to try them. They were clearly developed for other purposes, but as well, they generate the input of many miRNA pipelines. I just wanted to know how well my tool was doing. The first aim to develop miraligner was to get annotated additions of nucleotides at the end of miRNA sequences, something that is very common in mirna biogenesis: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IsomiR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;isomirs&lt;/a&gt; and often they are missed by short read and fast mappers. I have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/mypubs/tree/master/mirna/mirannotation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; for this kind of things, so anybody can reproduce my results, and check if I did something wrong, or comment on it. In this post I just want to know which tool detects more miRNA, for that I did two main steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simulate a bunch of miRNAs (isomirs) with my python &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/seqbuster/blob/master/misc/miRNA.simulator.py&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;script&lt;/a&gt; that is part of SeqBuster suit. I generated around 10000 sequences. Normally, one small-RNAseq library produces around half million different sequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use only miRBase human precursors as reference genome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used default parameter for all, so probably there is a set of parameters that would be better for some tools, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t search for them this time (happy to accept issues to add them). The &lt;a href=&#34;http://rawgit.com/lpantano/mypubs/master/mirna/mirannotation/stats.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;miraligner&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;STAR&lt;/strong&gt; map &lt;strong&gt;more sequences&lt;/strong&gt;. miraligner loses sequences shorter than 15 nt, normally (miRNA) are around 21, and those sequences map to repeat elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STAR is the best mapping, but need some parsing to reduce false positive. I think that pipelines should change to this tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GEM&lt;/strong&gt; has problems with &lt;strong&gt;additions and nt substitutions&lt;/strong&gt; in many cases, same as novoaligner (I will look at this in the future)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;bowtie2/bowtie is the second&lt;/strong&gt; that annotated most (and best)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;microrazer&lt;/strong&gt; has a problem with &lt;strong&gt;mismatches&lt;/strong&gt;, but maybe there is some parameter to trick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;miRExpress&lt;/strong&gt; with default options only will map perfect matches sequences to precursor, so strongly recommended to allow errors to increase sensibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say that the advantage of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/seqbuster/wiki/miraligner&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;miraligner&lt;/a&gt; is that it gives you the sequence annotated as miRNA or precursor, and gives you the exactly modifications that sequences have if they are compared to miRBase database. And you could feed the results to my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lpantano/seqbuster/wiki/isomiRs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R package&lt;/a&gt; to plot isomers distribution of samples from different groups, and do differential expression analysis with DESeq2, or another tool. I didn&amp;rsquo;t add time consumption because all of them run in a couple of minutes. In my next post I will focus in the the correct annotation of each sequence, and the possible problems with cross-mapping events, when the sequence comes from another regions of the genome but map to miRBase precursor as well [see my previous &lt;a href=&#34;http://lorenapantano.wordpress.com/2013/05/27/mirna-annotation-complex-scenarios/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; for more details]. As well I will use STAR with the full genome and see if the mapping continues being the best. In that case I will add a script to SeqBuster to parse the output of STAR for those who can map with STAR (need up to 32G for human genome)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomic analyses identify molecular subtypes of pancreatic cancer</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/bailey-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/bailey-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Specific small-RNA signatures in the amygdala at premotor and motor stages of Parkinson&#39;s disease revealed by deep sequencing analysis.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The small RNA content of human sperm reveals pseudogene-derived piRNAs complementary to protein-coding genes.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2015-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2015-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Impact and Evolution of a Novel Human Polymorphic Inversion That Disrupts a Gene and Creates a Fusion Transcript</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/puig-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/puig-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paternal Diet Defines Offspring Chromatin State and Intergenerational Obesity</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/ost-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/ost-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>InvFEST, a database integrating information of polymorphic inversions in the human genome</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/martinez-fundichely-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/martinez-fundichely-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulation of miRNA strand selection: follow the leader?</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/meijer-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/meijer-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>small RNA abundance [miss-] viz</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2013-10-29-small-rna-abundance-miss-viz/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 08:05:56 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2013-10-29-small-rna-abundance-miss-viz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My PhD was focused on small RNA sequencing data. I had a problem when I wanted to visualized the amount of small RNAs from the beginning. Here the problem, assume that you have a certain distribution of small RNA sequences abundance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;seq1: 1500 times&lt;br&gt;
seq2: 3 times&lt;br&gt;
seq3: 2 times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you want to show the nucleotide composition of the first nucleotide. You can do it either counting the # of sequences (or abundance) in your set (1505) or the number of unique (different) sequences (3). You result will be very bias depending on that. If you go for the first option, you can obtain:&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/ntabundance11.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/ntabundance11.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1000px&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and if you go for the second option:&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/ntabundance2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/ntabundance2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1000px&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is the best option? well, although papers in small RNA data still continue showing the first option, I think that this should be validated some way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When using unique sequences (only counting different sequences), you can under-estimated the real signal. In NGS, you can have a lot of noise, that may hide the biological signal using this approach. But, you can get the same, if you use directly the abundance, because if your set contains one sequence that is 90% of the data, you will get always a signal, that may be not important, for instance, ribosomal RNA that is expected to be there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution is to plot the data according both values: percentage of abundance and percentage of unique sequences. And you can do this for each position and nucleotide.&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/ntabundance3.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/ntabundance3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1000px&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can conclude that at position 1, there are few sequences starting with A that are  90 of the data. Also we can see how the 60% of unique sequences have a G at position 10. This helps us to catch any biological signature if it exists, and avoid the misleading information in this kind of figures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lying factor in figures</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2013-08-07-lying-factor-in-figures/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 11:36:25 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2013-08-07-lying-factor-in-figures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the lying factor in figures?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the ratio between the difference of two numbers and the difference of the visualization of those two numbers. For instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have two groups, each group is represented by 4 and 2. The difference between 4 and 2 is 2. Since &amp;ldquo;a picture is worth a thousand words&amp;rdquo;, someone decides to represents those groups in a figure (yes, in excel to make it worst):&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/lyingfactor.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/lyingfactor.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1000px&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That figure shows a difference of 4 between the two groups. Since 4 is twice than 2, we have a lying factor of 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably you think that this is not happening anywhere, it is ridiculous. It is, but probably you will find one of these cases in the news every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this is happening in science as well. For instance a (Nature) paper which explains how authors are improving a method that analyzes NGS data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They visualised a matrix correlation of the data using one method or another (b or c).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;![Screen Shot 2013-08-05 at 12.15.55 PM]({{ site.url }}/assets/screen-shot-2013-08-05-at-12-15-55-pm.png)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you only read colours, you won&amp;rsquo;t see much difference, but there is. The problem was to use a different colour scale to show the same type of data. Probably they were produced separately, so the command to produce those figures (probably an R function) had to guess the scale by its own, resulting that 0.89 is equal to 0.75 .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I leave my post here, and may say: take some time to think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;source:http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nbt.2596&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>miRNA annotation: complex scenarios</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2013-05-27-mirna-annotation-complex-scenarios/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 10:13:02 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2013-05-27-mirna-annotation-complex-scenarios/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Everybody who is working with microRNA knows about miRBase, it was the first miRNA catalogue. Everybody is using it to annotate small RNA sequences as miRNA or not. And it is great, and very helpfully&amp;hellip;but there are some cases that we should investigate our results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, what happens with miR-1246? it is a recent miRNA, primate specific, detected by sequencing in different studies (1,2,3). The counts related to these sequences are not so high, actually very low after normalization, but still are there. miRBase gives a precursor this region: chr2: 177465708-177465780 [-]&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-fig-1-mir1246&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/mir1246.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Fig 1: mir1246&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/mir1246.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fig 1: mir1246
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that there is a repeat element (ERV, retrovirus) and also it is a pretty conserved region. Until here, everything allright. But, I realized some time ago, annotating some data that I had, that the mature miRNA annotates in other regions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;chr:start-end strand&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;type&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;conservation&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;chr13:21,186,304-21,186,473 +&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;U2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;human&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;chr14:96,850,961-96,851,148 +&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;U2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rhesus&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;chr5:157,403,780-157,403,964 -&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;U2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rhesus&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;chr6:89,773,226-89,773,409 -&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;U2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rhesus&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;chr13:46,948,540-46,948,725 -&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;U2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rhesus&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;chr3:127,793,920-127,794,092 -&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;U2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rhesus&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;chr2:177,465,708-177,465,780 -&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;miR-1246&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rhesus,mouse,dog,elephant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of them are copies of a RNA repeat according RepBase, specifically the snRNA U2 class (150-200 nt). In addition, I got much more reads inside those (extra) locations than inside the annotated precursor (3 orders bigger). Furthermore, all of them had a peak in their coverage profile (fig 2).&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-fig-2reads-coverage-of-u2&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/u2-3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Fig 2:Reads coverage of U2&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/u2-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fig 2:Reads coverage of U2
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that arises now: is this a real miRNA, or a sub-product, or both? with any function? Maybe there is more than one precursor, or maybe it is a miRNA-like snRNA. Moreover, the secondary structure of these U2 is very similar to a miRNA precursor hairpin (fig 3).&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-fig-3u2-secondary-structure&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/u2-ss-strand.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Fig 3:U2 secondary structure&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/u2-ss-strand.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fig 3:U2 secondary structure
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cause of this annotation could be that the unique precursor conserved beyond primates is the one mentioned in miRBase, while the other U2 locations are primate-specific. Extra analyses should be done to reveal the real nature of this miRNA. Results suggest that, either the miRNA has more than one precursor, or a sub-product, or both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an extra-analysis, I took public data, KO Dicer and control, of HELA cells (GSM769512) to study the dependency od these sequences to DICER. You expect a decrease in the number of counts of miRNA sequences, between control and KO dicer. The exact miRNA sequence decrease 1/3 in KO dicer cells, assuming a Dicer dependency, and take this sequence as a real miRNA. But, we have a lot of other sequences in the U2 regions, but not in the annotated precursor, and only differ in one extra nucleotide (Adenosine) at the beginning (miR-1246: AAUGGAUUUUUGGAGCAGG and U2: &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;AAUGGAUUUUUGGAGCAGG).This sequence can be annotated as miR-1246 if you allow 1 mismatch in the alignment (the A nt). This sequence had the same counts in normal cells and KO cells, suggesting that sequences from U2 are not Dicer-dependent. Summarizing, we have the mature annotated miRNA mapping in all these positions, and in addition, we have other sequences (one nt longer), that only map in the U2 positions. So, how we can differentiate what proportion of sequences comes from the precursors and what comes from the other positions? Well, one possibility is to detect the precursor by PCR in your samples, to assume that at least it is there, or try to see whether the coverage in the different locations makes sense more with one scenario or another&amp;hellip;Or maybe it is not a big deal, you have this small RNA, the question is whether it has any regulatory function or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, we may agree that it is better to double-check what is happening when annotating small RNAs, because there are many possibilities to take a wrong conclusion if you only believe in a preliminary analysis. Nowadays, data is increasing a lot, and scientists need to make a bunch of assumptions to obtain something, but be careful with those assumptions (indeed, they are needed to evolve in science) because you may be missing something else or getting something wrong or wasting your time with experiments to corroborate your computational results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] PMID:18583537&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;MicroRNA discovery and profiling in human embryonic stem cells by deep sequencing of small RNA libraries&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
Bar M, Wyman SK, Fritz BR, Qi J, Garg KS, Parkin RK, Kroh EM, Bendoraite A, Mitchell PS, Nelson AM, Ruzzo WL, Ware C, Radich JP, Gentleman R, Ruohola-Baker H, Tewari M&lt;br&gt;
Stem Cells. 26:2496-2505(2008).&lt;br&gt;
[2] PMID:20300190&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Characterization of the Melanoma miRNAome by Deep Sequencing&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
Stark MS, Tyagi S, Nancarrow DJ, Boyle GM, Cook AL, Whiteman DC, Parsons PG, Schmidt C, Sturm RA, Hayward NK&lt;br&gt;
PLoS One. 5:e9685(2010).&lt;br&gt;
[3] PMID:20459774&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Ultra-high throughput sequencing-based small RNA discovery and discrete statistical biomarker analysis in a collection of cervical tumours and matched controls&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
Witten D, Tibshirani R, Gu SG, Fire A, Lui WO&lt;br&gt;
BMC Biol. 8:58(2010).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A highly expressed miR-101 isomiR is a functional silencing small RNA.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/llorens-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/llorens-2013/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microarray and deep sequencing cross-platform analysis of the mirRNome and isomiR variation in response to epidermal growth factor.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/llorens-2013-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/llorens-2013-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>visualizing small RNA mapping complexity</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2012-09-18-visualizing-small-rna-mapping-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 12:10:24 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2012-09-18-visualizing-small-rna-mapping-complexity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent all my PhD working with small RNA sequences data. The main problem was, always those sequences that map in multiple locations, also denominated ambiguous sequences. From the very beginning, this made that pipelines remove this kind of sequences from the analysis, because you cannot assign them a unique location in the genome. But these sequences are interesting to study, since many of them change in size, for instance. This complexity is due to repeats in the genome and the scenario I am talking about here it is shown in the following figure: ![]({{ site.url }}/assets/example1.png)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each color it would be a different sRNA, and the lines show the locations of each sRNA. There are location shared by some of the sRNAs, and you can easily transform this into a network of vertexes and edges, where vertexes are locations and edges, are their relationship coming from the sRNAs inside them. In this case it would generate three circles connected between them. And that it was I did with a real data set. I used &lt;a href=&#34;http://igraph.sourceforge.net/&#34; title=&#34;igraph&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;igraph&lt;/a&gt; in R to represent this with the help of this great &lt;a href=&#34;http://nsaunders.wordpress.com/2010/04/21/experiments-with-igraph/&#34; title=&#34;igraph tutorial&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. The result is:&lt;/p&gt;

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
   
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 &lt;figure &gt;
 
 
   &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/network.png&#34; &gt;
 
 
   &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/network.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34; &gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
 
 
 
 &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to detect high complexity regions, where locations are connected because some sRNAs map to anywhere else. From here, you can add more information, as the average size of the sRNAs inside each location, or the expression (red: low, yellow:high).   ![]({{ site.baseurl }}/assets/net-exp-3.png &amp;ldquo;network of sRNA complexity&amp;rdquo;) In a quick view you can check the complexity of your small RNA data and the expression associated. The code is published at &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpubs.com/lpantano/1719&#34; title=&#34;sRNA mappability&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rpub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing science is also cool @polychart</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2012-08-14-visualizing-science-is-also-cool-polychart/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2012 15:28:12 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2012-08-14-visualizing-science-is-also-cool-polychart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my interest in science is finding new ways to visualize Big Data. Scientist are used to work with static visualization, that of course, is wonderful in the majority of the case. But it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be better dynamic visualization for exploration? Play with your data, explore, and finally when you get that great figure that tell you everything you was looking for, you can export it to an image portable format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I played many time with javascript/HTML5 resources, but are no so easy to implement if you are not an expert, and some times, huge data makes difficult the easy interaction. Well, recently I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://polychart.com/&#34; title=&#34;polychart&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Polychart&lt;/a&gt;, is still in beta version, but I am using one of the feature they provide: Graph builder. And this is how it looks like after loading a file with 5000 rows and 37 columns:&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/polychart.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/polychart.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1000px&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make different type of charts, like boxplot, barplot, piechart (although aren&amp;rsquo;t well considered) etc. Also, you can customize titles and transform data. Quick complete for a beta version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally but not less important, it is free for academics. :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bionformatics evolution 2005-2012</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2012-04-13-bionformatics-evolution-2005-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 10:45:07 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/post/legacy/2012-04-13-bionformatics-evolution-2005-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How much keywords in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bioinformatics&#34; title=&#34;bioinformatics&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt; has changed in the past 7 years?&lt;br&gt;
I did a small and quick experiment. I took the abstract of the papers published in Bioinformatics during Jan-2005 and during Jan-2012. Then I represented the words according to their frequency with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordle.net/&#34; title=&#34;wordle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;wordle&lt;/a&gt; tool. And the result was:&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/jan2005bioinformatics.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/jan2005bioinformatics.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;









  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/jan2012bioinformatics.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;http://lpantano.github.io/media/images/jan2012bioinformatics.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is main difference? There are new concepts, of course, but the main difference is the size of the word DATA and the word METHOD, as it happens in the real world, data increased a lot, so we put it much more in our work, and we need a lof of new methods, so we highlight this in our work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Pathogenic Mechanism in Huntington&#39;s Disease Involves Small CAG-Repeated RNAs with Neurotoxic Activity.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/banez-coronel-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/banez-coronel-2012/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A non-biased framework for the annotation and classification of the non-miRNA small RNA transcriptome.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2011/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A myriad of miRNA variants in control and Huntington&#39;s disease brain regions detected by massively parallel sequencing</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/marti-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/marti-2010/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SeqBuster, a bioinformatic tool for the processing and analysis of small RNAs datasets, reveals ubiquitous miRNA modifications in human embryonic cells</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2010/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fibroblast-derived induced pluripotent stem cells show no common retroviral vector insertions.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/varas-2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/varas-2009/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Copy Number Variants Defining Genomic Differences among Major Human Groups</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/armengol-2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/armengol-2009/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ProSeeK: A web server for MLPA probe design</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/pantano-2008/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Highlights from the Third International Society for Computational Biology Student Council Symposium at the Fifteenth Annual International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/grynberg-2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/grynberg-2007/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome assembly comparison identifies structural variants in the human genome.</title>
      <link>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/khaja-2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lpantano.github.io/publication/khaja-2006/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
